<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The freedom of preaching or Spiritual gifts defended: proving that all men endowed with gifts and abilities may teach and preach the Word of God. By D. Lupton, servant of Jesus Christ in the work of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1331_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209106</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868006</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88650)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 176:E1331[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The freedom of preaching or Spiritual gifts defended: proving that all men endowed with gifts and abilities may teach and preach the Word of God. By D. Lupton, servant of Jesus Christ in the work of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.W. for R. Harford, at the Bible and States Arms in Little-Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 16.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Preaching --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lay preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169784:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Freedom of</hi> PREACHING, OR Spiritual Gifts defended: <hi>PRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ING</hi> That all men endowed with Gifts and Abilities may Teach and Preach the Word of God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 11. 29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Envieſt thou for this? Would God all the Lords People were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his Spirit upon them.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mar. 9. 38, 39, 40.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>We ſaw one caſting out Devils in thy Name, and we forbad him, becauſe be followeth not us.</p>
               <p>But Jeſus ſaid, forbid him not, for there is no man which ſhall do a miracle in my name, can lightly ſpeak cvil of me; for he that is not againſt us is on our ſide.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 14. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I would that ye all ſpake with tongues, but rather that ye Propheſied.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>D. Lupton,</hi> Servant of Jeſus Chriſt in the work of the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.W.</hi> for <hi>R. Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Stateſ Arms</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:169784:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169784:2"/>
            <head>The Freedom of Preaching, or, <hi>Spirituall Gifts defended.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 14.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Covet Spiritual Gifts, but rather that ye may Propheſie, or <hi>Preach.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome occaſions of buſineſs forcing my ſtay in London for awhile, I did (as opportunity would give leave) hear ſome teachers of Gods Word, at preſent <hi>reputed,</hi> and adjuged <hi>famous</hi> Divines; but certain it is, that fame and common report over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>values them, for even in their pulpits they could not forbear to ſet forth their <hi>ſpleen</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> even againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> perſons as deſerve a <hi>better</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169784:3"/>eſteem, if it be but for their <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>excellent</hi> gifts and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> abilities, with which it hath pleaſed God to <hi>entruſt</hi> and <hi>enrich</hi> them; and what is more;</p>
            <p>In a great Congregation. <hi>(viz.)</hi> Sepulchers, upon a <hi>Lords day</hi> in the <hi>Afternoon;</hi> it was <hi>publickly</hi> preached, that gifts were not to be regarded; that they <hi>puffed</hi> men up, that it was a <hi>ſure</hi> ſign of an Hypocrite, and of a <hi>withering</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to ſhew his gifts, and <hi>to ſtand</hi> upon his <hi>abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of gifts, (and yet himſelf was then exerciſing his gifts, and as 'tis <hi>known</hi> well) he did <hi>ſtrive</hi> to ſet forth his <hi>able</hi> gift of preaching <hi>to the full,</hi> and would be very <hi>angry,</hi> if any ſhould tell him that he <hi>wants</hi> gifts and parts, and yet to undervalue <hi>men of gifts;</hi> he made an oppoſition betwixt Graces and gifts, which though they may <hi>ſometime</hi> in ſome perſons be ſeparated, yet <hi>uſually</hi> they go together, and may very well be both in one and the ſame perſon at once; as he conceivs they are in himſelf, but thinks not poſſible to be in others.</p>
            <p>Upon hearing <hi>this,</hi> I enquired of a friend upon what <hi>occaſion</hi> the Presbyterian Rabbies did ſo violently expreſs <hi>their ſpleen</hi> and <hi>indignation,</hi> and againſt <hi>whom</hi> it was; He told me that there were divers <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> and <hi>Artiſts,</hi> in and about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> who <hi>Preach'd</hi> and <hi>Teached</hi> the word, and yet never were in any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> nor were ever made <hi>Miniſters</hi> by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of Divines,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169784:3"/>and <hi>ſuch men</hi> they could not <hi>abide,</hi> nor <hi>endure</hi> that they ſhould have <hi>liberty</hi> to preach, and that <hi>of late</hi> they were more <hi>countenanced</hi> by ſome <hi>great</hi> Perſonages, to the great ſcandal (as they ſay) of the <hi>publike</hi> Miniſtery, and to the <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> of many that hear them, and their <hi>Pernicious</hi> Doctrines, and to the <hi>venting</hi> of sects and <hi>damnable</hi> Hereſies, and (as they would make men believe) to the <hi>deſtruction</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> of the Church and Common-Wealth.</p>
            <p>Being thus <hi>informed</hi> by a friend, I did <hi>reſolve</hi> with my ſelf, to ſet forth my <hi>own</hi> judgment, and ſatisfie <hi>others</hi> in this particular, &amp;hereupon ſet pen to paper, to <hi>cleer</hi> and <hi>vindicate</hi> ſuch <hi>gifted</hi> men in their <hi>actions</hi> of Preaching Gods <hi>Word,</hi> from theſe <hi>too virulent</hi> and <hi>violent</hi> Spirits of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Claſſis, who <hi>vainly</hi> think, that <hi>none</hi> have any <hi>Talents</hi> but themſelves, or that <hi>none</hi> (having any Talents) may <hi>imploy them</hi> publikely <hi>to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers,</hi> without <hi>leave</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> from their <hi>Elderſhips</hi> firſt had and obtained: though the texts ſayes plainly; <hi>Thou oughteſt to have put my mony to the Exchangers;</hi> Mat. 25.27. Thou, 'tis not onely <hi>thou</hi> (O Presbyterian alone) but I, and <hi>others</hi> too, and <hi>ought</hi> to have done it; <hi>urget ſingulos ab officio:</hi> from every mans duty: to put out <hi>his</hi> or <hi>their</hi> talent to the greateſt <hi>augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of Gods glory, and to the <hi>generall</hi> bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and edification of mens ſouls.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169784:4"/>
            <p>To uphold this <hi>truth</hi> therefore, which is ſo <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently</hi> oppoſed, but not poſſible to be <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown,</hi> no, not by all the Company of thoſe <hi>learned</hi> Rabbies; whoſe <hi>Anger</hi> would not be ſo <hi>extream</hi> againſt ſpiritual <hi>gifted men,</hi> but that they <hi>fear,</hi> if theſe be <hi>followed</hi> or <hi>ſet up,</hi> that they <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> and their <hi>places of profit</hi> will in ſhort time be <hi>ſlighted</hi> and <hi>diſſallowed</hi> off, thinking as thoſe <hi>wicked</hi> Prieſts did of our Saviour Chriſt, <hi>if we let him alone, all men will follow him.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm <hi>this point</hi> therefore, and <hi>to make it good</hi> to the world, I lay down theſe <hi>following</hi> Arguments; which I deſire <hi>all</hi> that read them <hi>ſeriouſly,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with themſelves concerning them; and let the Presbyterian <hi>benefic'd</hi> Rabbies, aſ ſoon as they can, anſwer them; or elſe if their <hi>proud</hi> Spirits will <hi>permit</hi> it, to <hi>embrace</hi> them, and <hi>ſubmit</hi> to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the <hi>publike</hi> preaching, or <hi>teaching</hi> of Gods <hi>word</hi> is not <hi>reſtrained</hi> or <hi>confin'd,</hi> nor <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted</hi> to <hi>any one</hi> ſort or <hi>condition</hi> of men onely; but that <hi>any one,</hi> of any calling (if a Member of the Church of Chriſt) though of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> ſort, if <hi>he</hi> or <hi>they</hi> be <hi>endowed</hi> with <hi>gifts</hi> proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, by the Spirit of God, to <hi>execute</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe</hi> the work, may <hi>Preach</hi> or <hi>teach</hi> publickly, aſ well as our <hi>great</hi> Schollers, who ſtand ſo much upon <hi>their corrupted Ordination.</hi> Thus proved.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169784:4"/>
            <p>Firſt, From the <hi>manner</hi> of Gods <hi>beſtowing</hi> and giving his <hi>ſpiritual</hi> gifts; <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5. He doth not beſtow <hi>all</hi> upon <hi>one</hi> ſervant, and <hi>nothing</hi> upon another; but he diſtributes <hi>to all</hi> as he pleaſeth; So that if <hi>any man;</hi> the holy Apoſtle doth not ſay <hi>this man</hi> onely, or <hi>that</hi> (as the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or Dr. in the <hi>Schools</hi>) but <hi>if any man, poor</hi> or <hi>rich, learned</hi> or <hi>unlearned, lack Wiſdom, Let him ask it of God, who giveth to all men liberally, and upbr aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not:</hi> as to ſay, you are not in <hi>holy</hi> Orders; the Biſhops, nor <hi>Presbyters</hi> have laid no hands <hi>upon you,</hi> you are not <hi>fit</hi> or <hi>worthy,</hi> or the like; No, <hi>be upbraideth not,</hi> (and ſaid the text) It (<hi>i.e.</hi>) Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall be given to him, to <hi>any; James</hi> 1.5. Now to <hi>ſumm</hi> up what is for our <hi>purpoſe,</hi> we ſee, that if any man, <hi>Tradeſman, Artificer,</hi> though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo mean, if he or they <hi>pray</hi> to God <hi>in faith,</hi> for <hi>wiſdom,</hi> which is the <hi>onely</hi> Ornament and <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> gift for a Preacher; and it is not expreſſed <hi>what wiſdom,</hi> it may be <hi>Wiſdom</hi> not onely <hi>to ſearch,</hi> but to <hi>expound</hi> and <hi>interpret</hi> the Scriptures; why, <hi>that</hi> ſhall be <hi>given,</hi> and <hi>liberally</hi> too, and to <hi>any</hi> one; Here's no <hi>confining</hi> or <hi>limiting,</hi> or <hi>excepting,</hi> or <hi>preferring</hi> of perſons, <hi>For God is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter of perſons.</hi> Nay further, he many times fills the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>hungry</hi> with <hi>good things,</hi> with graces and <hi>gifts</hi> of his holy Spirit, to enable them <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe</hi> in their own <hi>conceit,</hi> and <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> too, but ſends the <hi>rich</hi> (in <hi>Schollerſhip,</hi> in <hi>Parts,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169784:5"/>in <hi>Arts,</hi> in <hi>Preferments,</hi> by outward <hi>Ordination</hi> and calling to the <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> Miniſtry of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) <hi>empty away;</hi> and ſhall ſuch <hi>great</hi> Presbyters, who yet may <hi>be empty</hi> of theſe <hi>good</hi> things, be the <hi>onely</hi> Teachers and Preachers <hi>allowed to be</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and <hi>deſpiſe,</hi> (and as <hi>much</hi> as in them <hi>lies</hi>) hinder and <hi>exclude</hi> the poor in <hi>worldly</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, (though end owed <hi>with Wiſdom</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) from <hi>Preaching</hi> Gods word <hi>Freely;</hi> What, <hi>is their eye evil,</hi> becauſe <hi>Gods eye is good?</hi> or ſhall God <hi>give</hi> to any <hi>without upbraiding,</hi> and ſhall theſe Presbyters <hi>Rail, Accuſe, Revile</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> ſuch for <hi>Sectaries,</hi> whom God <hi>enables</hi> and <hi>approves</hi> off? Shall God of his Royal <hi>Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> give to <hi>any,</hi> and ſhall <hi>theſe</hi> grudge or <hi>repine</hi> at it? ſince <hi>he</hi> hath made his <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>gifts</hi> free, ſhall <hi>theſe onely</hi> perſwade men, that <hi>all</hi> are <hi>empty</hi> but themſelves? away with ſuch <hi>ridiculous</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures and <hi>deluſions;</hi> for ſince <hi>any other man</hi> may have <hi>wiſdom</hi> from God, aſ well as <hi>themſelves,</hi> nay many <hi>ſooner</hi> and <hi>plentifuller</hi> than themſelves, why may they not <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>preach aſ well,</hi> if not <hi>better</hi> than <hi>themſelves?</hi> Every Preacher ſhould be <hi>Endowed with wiſdom from above;</hi> If Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and <hi>Mechanicks</hi> (as they are <hi>called</hi> in ſcorn) be <hi>full of wiſdom, let</hi> them, <hi>any of them</hi> preach, and <hi>preach</hi> freely.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To proceed to a ſecond Argument; for in ſo doing they do but what God would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169784:5"/>have them do; for to this end and intent God beſtows <hi>his gifts;</hi> as he gives them to any <hi>that ask,</hi> ſo he gives them <hi>to be Imployed,</hi> and <hi>mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> and <hi>Improved;</hi> they will not be <hi>the lighter</hi> but the <hi>brighter</hi> for being uſed; this ſhall be made plain, as we may <hi>ſee it</hi> by our Saviours own words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Neither do men light a Candle and put it under a Buſhel, but on a Candleſtick, and it giveth light to all that are in the houſe:</hi> and ſo Mark. 4.21. <hi>Is a candle brought to be put under a Buſhel, or under a Bed? and not to be ſet on a Candleſtick?</hi> and Luk 8.16. <hi>No man when he hath lighted a Candle, covereth it with a veſſel, or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it under a Bed, but ſetteth it on a Candleſtick, that all that enter in may ſee the light;</hi> and ſo Paul to Timothy, <hi>Stir up the gift that is in thee.</hi> 1 Tim. 4.13. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p and be doing, and the Lord be with thee. Thou oughteſt to have put my mony to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers.</hi> Mat. 25.27. Now to <hi>Collect</hi> for our <hi>purpoſe</hi> out of <hi>theſe</hi> places; three of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts <hi>agree</hi> that a Candle is not to be <hi>hid</hi> or <hi>obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi> Men <hi>uſe not</hi> ſo to do, ſays <hi>Matthew,</hi> there is no ſuch order; nay, its againſt <hi>Common practice,</hi> is a Candle brought, ſays <hi>Mark;</hi> No ſure, there's none hath <hi>ſo little</hi> reaſon, or <hi>judgment</hi> to do ſo; <hi>No man</hi> (ſays Luke) <hi>when he hath lighted a Candle;</hi> For 'tis againſt all <hi>common</hi> benefic, tis to give <hi>light,</hi> and to be <hi>ſet up,</hi> it guides <hi>all,</hi> and <hi>lightens</hi> all that <hi>enter in,</hi> or that are <hi>in the houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169784:6"/>
            <p>To come <hi>cloſer</hi> yet to our intendment; whats <hi>reſembled</hi> by the Candle, but <hi>Illumination, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning grace</hi> of God in the Soul, or Gods word is the <hi>Candle</hi> in the ſoul, the <hi>cleer</hi> underſtanding the Scriptures, <hi>knowledge</hi> of them; when God doth <hi>lighten</hi> this Candle in <hi>any</hi> man, of what <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> or <hi>calling</hi> ſoever, for there's no man (but ſome groſs Malefactors are <hi>debarred</hi> from a <hi>Candle</hi> from <hi>light,</hi>) the pooreſt man that is, will endeavour to have a <hi>Candle</hi> ſet up in his houſe; We ſay, when it doth <hi>pleaſe</hi> God to do ſo, (as he uſeth) why, ſuch men that are ſo <hi>inlightned</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are <hi>to give light</hi> to others, by <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> preaching and <hi>living;</hi> Nay, they are to be <hi>ſet up,</hi> why not in Publick Congregations? they are not to be <hi>ſuppreſt</hi> or <hi>kept under</hi> by any <hi>cenſures</hi> of the <hi>pretending</hi> Presbyters but let them be as 'tis fitting and ſeemly <hi>advanced, ſet up,</hi> that they may <hi>teach,</hi> give <hi>light</hi> to them that <hi>ſit in darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing that God <hi>lights theſe Candles,</hi> who dare <hi>ſnuff</hi> at him, or them? or ſtrive <hi>to blow them out,</hi> or pull them down? will our Rabbies <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men</hi> that none can have Candles <hi>lighted</hi> but they, or that no <hi>Candles</hi> muſt <hi>ſhine</hi> and <hi>burn</hi> but in <hi>their</hi> houſes or <hi>ſtudies?</hi> or that <hi>none</hi> knows how to <hi>light</hi> a Candle but they? will they be <hi>ſo uncharitable</hi> (as 'tis to be feared they would, had they but <hi>the power</hi> in <hi>their hands,</hi> which they have long <hi>gaped</hi> after) as to <hi>blow out</hi> all other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169784:6"/>mens <hi>Candles,</hi> that theirs may <hi>burn</hi> alone.</p>
            <p>Did God ſay, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>Let there be light,</hi> and for all <hi>equally</hi> to enjoy, and will yet theſe men <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>grudge</hi> that other men <hi>have light</hi> aſ well and as <hi>freely</hi> as themſelves? Or yet further, will they, or dare they be angry that other mens <hi>Cand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> give light, <hi>better</hi> light, <hi>purer</hi> light, <hi>more</hi> light, <hi>freer</hi> light then theirs do, or can do? or do they <hi>vex</hi> themſelves that there is <hi>ſo many</hi> lights, <hi>new</hi> and <hi>true</hi> lights ſet up every where, or almoſt in every Corner? Do they not <hi>grudge</hi> to ſee how <hi>their Candles</hi> burn <hi>dimmer</hi> and <hi>dimmer,</hi> and tis to be feared will go <hi>ſhortly</hi> and <hi>ſuddenly</hi> out in a <hi>ſtinking, noyſome</hi> ſmell? Oh my friends, look well to it; Shall not others <hi>work while they have the light,</hi> aſ well and <hi>better</hi> than you have done, ſince God Commands <hi>all</hi> to work, and hath lent them <hi>light,</hi> and ſet up their Candle? then hinder them not, do not longer ſtrive <hi>to extinguiſh</hi> the light in any man; I wiſh you in this matter, to <hi>accept</hi> of that <hi>good</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Counſel</hi> of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel, Take heed what ye intend to do as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe men, refrain I ſay from theſe men,</hi> Act 5. ver. 35.36.37.38. <hi>and let them alone; for if this Counſel, or this work be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, (as it was then, and is indeed now) ye cannot overthrow it, leſt haply ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi> Thats our ſecond argument, God gives his gifts to all, to edifie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169784:7"/>
               <hi>not to be idle;</hi> whoſoever then hath <hi>the gift of Propheſying</hi> or <hi>Preaching,</hi> let him or them <hi>uſe it</hi> to the utmoſt; <hi>deſire ſpiritual gifts</hi> (ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>by prayer, but rather that ye may Propheſie,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.1, 2, 3, 4. And yet he writ <hi>that</hi> to <hi>all</hi> the Corinthians, not onely to the Presbyters; <hi>but to the whole Church at Corinth, yes, and to all that in every place call upon the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. And yet <hi>all theſe</hi> are to deſire that they may be <hi>able to Preach</hi> and <hi>Teach</hi> the Word; for certain the Apoſtle would never have wiſhed <hi>to pray</hi> to God, that they might <hi>all</hi> Propheſie, or Preach, if it had been <hi>unlawfull;</hi> and to ſtir up them <hi>more earneſtly</hi> to it, he ſhews them the <hi>Excellent</hi> benefit and profit of <hi>Preaching:</hi> 1 Cor. 14.3, 4. <hi>He (ſays the Apoſtle) any one, or every one that Propheſieth, ſpeaketh to Edification, exhortation and comfort, but I had rather</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that ye could all Propheſie:</hi> Mark there, he ſays <hi>All.</hi> Alſo to the Romans, <hi>having then gifts,</hi> that is, aſ ſoon as God hath beſtowed gifts upon any, <hi>differing according to the Grace that is given to us, whether Propheſie, let us Propheſie according to the proportion of faith:</hi> Rom. 12.6. Whatſoever the <hi>gift</hi> be, it <hi>ought not</hi> to be <hi>concealed,</hi> but <hi>Imployed,</hi> there's the <hi>End</hi> of it; if it <hi>pleaſeth</hi> God to give <hi>the gift</hi> of Propheſie, <hi>preſently</hi> to the work, <hi>Preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon;</hi> 1 Tim. 4.2, 3. And yet the Apoſtle doth not <hi>tye</hi> this <hi>Preaching</hi> to any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169784:7"/>one <hi>particular</hi> calling, <hi>ſect</hi> or perſon, but to <hi>All that be in Rome, beloved of God.</hi> Rom. 1.7. and by conſequence, why may not <hi>All</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> as well as <hi>All</hi> in <hi>Rome, if gifted</hi> with Propheſie, Preach the word of God? and yet this <hi>done</hi> by Apoſtolical <hi>exhortation.</hi> Away then with all ſuch <hi>Sophiſticated</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Maximes,</hi> that would fain <hi>tye up</hi> the Diſpenſation of Chriſts <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> to their <hi>libits</hi> and as they did <hi>for gains</hi> pull the Biſhops out of <hi>their</hi> chairs, ſo for <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Lucre</hi> they would have <hi>none</hi> excerciſe <hi>the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of God <hi>Word,</hi> but who ſhould <hi>paſs</hi> the cenſure of <hi>their</hi> Approbation, as if Gods word was to be <hi>No where,</hi> nor by <hi>any perſons</hi> taught, but where and by whom their <hi>ignorant</hi> zeal ſhall think fit. Oh ſtupid ignorance!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, 'Tis <hi>lawfull</hi> for any that is <hi>gifted,</hi> to Preach; from the <hi>Approbation, conſent,</hi> and <hi>good liking</hi> of the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>holieſt</hi> men that ever were: We'l begin with that ſtory recorded by <hi>Moſes</hi>'s pen: <hi>Num.</hi> 11.28, 29, 30. <hi>Moſes</hi> found <hi>the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs</hi> of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained unto God, that he was <hi>not able</hi> to bear the <hi>burthen</hi> of them <hi>any longer;</hi> and God bids him gather ſeventy of the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> together, and he would take of <hi>the Spirit</hi> from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and put it upon the Elders: Obſerve <hi>how</hi> God gives the <hi>Spirit</hi> to whom and when <hi>he pleaſeth;</hi> 'tis not tyed <hi>more</hi> to a Presbyterian Elder, or Rabbi,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169784:8"/>than 'tis <hi>to a Porter</hi> or <hi>a Carman:</hi> But when theſe ſeventy Elders did <hi>come up,</hi> there were <hi>two</hi> that ſtaid behind, <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> by name; and whereas it might be thought <hi>a ſin</hi> that they came not up; and might have been <hi>ſuſpected</hi> not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for to <hi>receive</hi> the Spirit, yet God gave it <hi>not onely</hi> to the Elders who came up; For they all propheſied ver. 25. <hi>and ceaſed not;</hi> but alſo to thoſe two <hi>who came not up,</hi> for they <hi>alſo</hi> did <hi>Propheſie</hi> in the Camp, <hi>among the Soldiers;</hi> and indeed <hi>their Practice</hi> was thought ſtrange, for <hi>there ran a yong man, and told Moſes</hi> that theſe two did <hi>Preach</hi> among the <hi>Soldiers,</hi> and <hi>Jofhua</hi> out of his <hi>zeal</hi> preſently did (as out Presbyters would have done now) <hi>fobid them,</hi> by all means (my Lord <hi>Moſes</hi>) ſays <hi>Joſhua, forbid them,</hi> never ſuffer ſuch a thing as this is; <hi>they came not up at your ſummons,</hi> and what <hi>this</hi> may come to, <hi>if ſuffered,</hi> cannot be imagined, it cannot <hi>be good,</hi> for ſure <hi>they preach</hi> without the Spirit of God, the <hi>other</hi> Elders we <hi>know</hi> have it, but how theſe ſhould have it, I know not, and to let <hi>ſuch as they are</hi> propheſie and <hi>Preach</hi> in the Camp, it may be <hi>very dangerous,</hi> for they may <hi>perſwade men</hi> to neglect <hi>coming up</hi> to the <hi>Publike</hi> Ordinances, and ſo the <hi>Prieſts</hi> will be <hi>ſlighted,</hi> and the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> not <hi>regarded,</hi> and men will do <hi>as they pleaſe;</hi> forbid them (Oh my Lord) as you <hi>tender</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and the <hi>Sacriſices,</hi> and <hi>Oblations;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169784:8"/>ſhould be <hi>upheld,</hi> for the <hi>maintenance</hi> of the Prieſts and Levites? I pray <hi>forbid them</hi> forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; and as <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſo our Prieſts and others <hi>cry out</hi> againſt ſuch as <hi>Preach</hi> in the Armies, or without <hi>their</hi> Ordination and <hi>Impoſition of hands;</hi> Oh! <hi>would</hi> our Magiſtrates forbid them, 'tis <hi>a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor to Religion,</hi> and in <hi>ſhort</hi> time will make men <hi>not regard</hi> to come to Churches, or to the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and Tythes <hi>hereupon</hi> will be denyed, and <hi>we</hi> the Miniſters, The <hi>true, Orthodox, Godly,</hi> able, and onely Miniſters, ſhall be <hi>of no worth</hi> or <hi>eſteem,</hi> 'tis not <hi>fitting</hi> they ſhould <hi>Propheſie,</hi> they have no ſuch power from us. Oh! Good Parliament of <hi>England, forbid them,</hi> or elſe our calling goes down; Well, but as <hi>Moſes</hi> did anſwer <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſo will I do <hi>our</hi> men; <hi>envieſt thou for this?</hi> (ſays <hi>Moſes</hi>) Num. 1.29. <hi>Would to God that al the Lords people were Prophets, and that the Lord would put his Spirit upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To gather from hence: <hi>Moſes</hi> we ſee was <hi>ſo far</hi> from <hi>hindering</hi> that <hi>good work</hi> (though <hi>be had</hi> power, and <hi>Authority</hi> to have done it, and though he was <hi>deeply</hi> and <hi>earneſtly</hi> ſollicited by <hi>Joſhua</hi> to to put it <hi>in execution,</hi> and though <hi>it had not been uſed</hi> before, or practiſed in the Camp) that he ſeems <hi>rather</hi> to check <hi>Joſhua,</hi> for his deſiring <hi>to hinder</hi> them, than any ways to <hi>moleſt them</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Envieſt thou for this?</hi> ver. 28.29. What is this to you, you ſhould rather <hi>uphold</hi> and encourage the <hi>Preaching</hi> of Gods words, than be <hi>againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169784:9"/>ſuch</hi> as are willing <hi>to take pains</hi> to inſtruct others, you or thou! I had not thought <hi>you</hi> would <hi>ever</hi> have <hi>envied</hi> againſt a <hi>good</hi> work; It doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>thee</hi> to Envy at <hi>other mens</hi> good labours; It is <hi>ſo far</hi> from being <hi>evil</hi> or <hi>nought,</hi> as I wiſh <hi>heartily</hi> that <hi>all</hi> the people had <hi>the like</hi> gift, I would to God <hi>that they all</hi> could <hi>Propheſie;</hi> aſſure your ſelf (as you are <hi>my Servant</hi>) you ought not <hi>to grudge</hi> or envy at them, but rather to <hi>Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and <hi>encourage</hi> them, for <hi>they do</hi> the Lords <hi>work,</hi> and therefore <hi>let them alone,</hi> Envy not at it. <hi>Let them alone,</hi> 'tis Gods pleaſure and his will, and therefore <hi>let them alone;</hi> and thus may it be <hi>ſaid</hi> to all our <hi>Rigid Presbyters,</hi> why do ye <hi>Envy</hi> that <hi>others</hi> as well as your ſelves preach? is it <hi>fit</hi> for ſuch as you <hi>profeſs</hi> to be, ſhould be <hi>envious, angry</hi> men, and <hi>for this?</hi> that <hi>great are the company of of the Preachers?</hi> Pſal. 68.5. Shake off <hi>ſuch</hi> envy, you ſhould rather <hi>praiſe</hi> God for it, there will be <hi>the leſs work</hi> for you to undergo; are you <hi>ſtronger</hi> than <hi>Moſes?</hi> he was <hi>weary</hi> and not able <hi>to bear</hi> the burthen of all that people <hi>alone;</hi> are not many, <hi>too many</hi> of your Congregations <hi>too great</hi> for you? though you think not <hi>the means</hi> too much, nor yet enough; yet 'tis to be <hi>feard</hi> the people are <hi>too</hi> great and many for <hi>you</hi> to provide <hi>ſpiritual food</hi> for; how contrary are you to the mind of Chriſt; pray (ſays he) to my <hi>father, that he would ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt, the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169784:9"/>is great and the Labourers but few,</hi> Mat. 9.37.38. Many hands make like work, and therefore <hi>be thank full</hi> for it, that God is <hi>pleaſed</hi> in the <hi>latter dayes to poure out his ſpirit upon all fleſh,</hi> and that the <hi>Spirit</hi> reſts with <hi>others,</hi> though <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>baſe</hi> in your opinion: Shall <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſh that <hi>all</hi> the Lords people were <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Preachers,</hi> and will you ſpeak againſt it?</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Confirmation</hi> of this, yet a <hi>ſtep</hi> or <hi>two</hi> further: 'Tis recorded in the Goſpel written by <hi>Mark</hi> 9.38.39. of <hi>John,</hi> that he told our Saviour <hi>that they ſaw one caſting out Divels in his Name, and becauſe he did not follow them, they forbad him.</hi> But Jeſus ſaid, <hi>forbid him not, for he that is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, is on our part;</hi> Luk. 9.49. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did <hi>then,</hi> as many would do <hi>now,</hi> though they ſee that Gods <hi>work</hi> is done, and that the power of the Devil is daily <hi>weakned,</hi> yet becauſe there are <hi>ſome</hi> gifted by Gods <hi>bleſſed</hi> Spirit who Preach down ſin, and follow not the Presbyterian Way, they are preſently <hi>offended</hi> at them, and in all haſt they do what they can <hi>to hinder</hi> and <hi>forbid</hi> them in that <hi>great work</hi> of preaching: the Apoſtles might ſay, when they ſaw him caſting out Divels; Why do you <hi>exerciſe</hi> this Aughority? where is your <hi>power</hi> given you from Chriſt, <hi>ſhew</hi> your <hi>Orders,</hi> where did ever you <hi>receive</hi> ſuch commiſſion? We are the <hi>onely</hi> true Preachers, we are ſent by our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169784:10"/>Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, 'tis not <hi>fitting</hi> you ſhould <hi>Preach</hi> or Practice <hi>ſuch things,</hi> except you had <hi>a Warrant,</hi> or Calling from Chriſt, and therefore we <hi>forbid</hi> you: and ſo ſay our Presbyters <hi>too,</hi> even to <hi>ſuch</hi> men who are <hi>gifted</hi> with the Spirit, Why take <hi>you</hi> upon you to <hi>Teach</hi> and <hi>Preach?</hi> where were you <hi>ordained,</hi> how came you into the <hi>holy</hi> Miniſtry? what <hi>Claſſis,</hi> or <hi>Synodal Convention</hi> authorized you? What <hi>degrees</hi> in Schools or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities</hi> have you taken? and if not allowed by us who are <hi>the ſucceſſors</hi> of the Apoſtles, and can (but not as yet have, nor ever will be able to) prove our <hi>Ordination</hi> Divine; Why dare you, not being in holy <hi>Orders,</hi> undertake to Preach <hi>at all?</hi> but what reply made our Saviour; <hi>Forbid him not, for he that is not againſt us, is for us.</hi> Luke 9.49, 50. So it may be replied to our <hi>Apoſtolical conceited</hi> Rabbies, who judge none <hi>Able</hi> or <hi>fit</hi> but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the Miniſtry; <hi>forbid not</hi> theſe men, they do Chriſts work, they are for Chriſt, and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw</hi> the works of the Devil; rather <hi>help</hi> ſuch men <hi>forward,</hi> but <hi>by no means</hi> forbid them; Take heed you <hi>Quench not the Spirit in</hi> theſe men, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. though perhaps but <hi>tradeſmen,</hi> and the <hi>meaneſt</hi> too; <hi>Deſpiſe not Propheſying,</hi> not any, and <hi>reſiſt not the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Act. 7. Can you be <hi>juſtly</hi> angry that Chriſts Goſpel is <hi>propagated?</hi> What is it <hi>to you</hi> what <hi>Inſtruments</hi> God pleaſeth to <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>Imploy?</hi> What if it pleaſe God to ſend <hi>theſe</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169784:10"/>out to the <hi>Hedges, Highwaies</hi> and <hi>Lanes</hi> (whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>your ſtatelineſs</hi> will not vouchſafe to go) to call in the <hi>Halt,</hi> the <hi>Lame</hi> and the <hi>Blinde</hi> (to whom you will <hi>ſcorn</hi> to Preach, or with whom you do <hi>diſdain</hi> to converſe) if <hi>by this means</hi> Gods houſe be <hi>filled,</hi> and ſo the Saints <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered up</hi> together, have you any cauſe of Anger for their <hi>Compaſſion, Pains and Charity?</hi> And to <hi>ſhut</hi> up this Argument; What reaſon have you to <hi>diſable</hi> them, whom God hath <hi>enabled;</hi> or to <hi>debar</hi> them, whom God hath <hi>ſet up?</hi> or did the Goſpel come <hi>onely</hi> from you? or is it <hi>onely</hi> reſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your <hi>Claſſes?</hi> or are you angry that <hi>the Sun</hi> of Righteouſneſs <hi>ſhines</hi> into theſe mens <hi>ſhops</hi> more then into your <hi>Pulpits</hi> or <hi>Studies?</hi> or are you <hi>offended</hi> that the <hi>ſweet</hi> dew of the Spirit of Grace is <hi>ſhed abroad,</hi> and Communicated to <hi>poor</hi> Tradeſmen aſ wel as to others? <hi>He hath given gifts unto men,</hi> Pſal. 68. not onely to your ſelves, but to <hi>other</hi> men alſo; ſince therefore <hi>all</hi> are allowed by <hi>Moſes</hi> to Preach, and none for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by Chriſt, who do <hi>his</hi> work, Ceaſe any longer <hi>to cry up</hi> your ſelves for the <hi>onely</hi> men; and let others have <hi>liberty</hi> to hold out Chriſt in his word as well as your ſelves. <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> How can theſe men <hi>give</hi> freely, when you do <hi>all you can</hi> to ſtop their mouths? beware <hi>this Envy</hi> mines you not. There were four ſins that caſt our the Biſhops, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169784:11"/>firſt was their <hi>Secular</hi> Offices, and intermedling in <hi>State</hi> Affairs. The ſecond was, their <hi>Pride</hi> of life and <hi>Ambition.</hi> The third was their Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The fourth was their <hi>ſuppreſſing</hi> Godly men, and <hi>aſ much</hi> as in them <hi>lay,</hi> the very <hi>Power</hi> of Godlineſs. Look to it, if theſe be your ſins, they will <hi>caſt</hi> you down, and out of <hi>Moſes Chair</hi> ere long; make not your Pulpits <hi>Chairs</hi> of State, and your ſelves <hi>Councellors</hi> of State.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a great ſin for any man to hide his Talent; <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.28, 29. and a heavy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will they <hi>ſuffer</hi> that do not imploy Gods <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> in the <hi>higheſt</hi> degree and meaſure; and a <hi>great</hi> reward is promiſed by Chriſt <hi>to any,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> ſuch, who are <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>carefull</hi> to do the Lords work. We know how <hi>weak</hi> his excuſe was that pleaded he was afraid <hi>to put out</hi> his Maſters <hi>mony; I was afraid, and went and hid it, here is thine own;</hi> his fear of <hi>looſing</hi> it, or having it <hi>ſtole,</hi> or <hi>diminiſhed,</hi> made him <hi>hide</hi> it; yet <hi>none</hi> of theſe, nor <hi>all</hi> theſe, were a <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> anſwer to his Maſter. <hi>Thou ougheſt to put it out,</hi> Mat. 25.27. You ſhould not have feared <hi>loſs,</hi> God will ſo <hi>bleſs,</hi> and <hi>guide,</hi> and <hi>proſper</hi> his own <hi>work,</hi> that however, if his word ſhould <hi>return empty</hi> (which is impoſſible) yet the <hi>labourer</hi> ſhall not <hi>loſe</hi> his <hi>reward</hi> or <hi>recompence:</hi> And ſee how God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of this <hi>Servant</hi> that did not <hi>imploy</hi> his Talent, <hi>Thou wicked and ſloathfull Servant,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169784:11"/>Mat. 25.26. and <hi>take therefore the Talent from him.</hi> v. 28. and <hi>Caſt ye that unprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs,</hi> v. 29. <hi>Bleſſed is that Servant whom when his Maſter ſhall come, he ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi> Why not <hi>Preaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles <hi>indeed,</hi> according to our Saviour Chriſts <hi>Promiſe</hi> made to them, ſtaid at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> till they were <hi>endued with power from above,</hi> till they were <hi>filled</hi> with the Holy Ghoſt; but preſently after they went about all places, <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Teaching</hi> Jeſus Chriſt to Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; <hi>According as ye have received the gift,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle; and therefore <hi>all men,</hi> when once they have received <hi>the hidden Manna,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <hi>tincture</hi> of Gods Spirit, they cannot <hi>but ſpeak,</hi> as the Apoſtle Peter, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.5, 6. <hi>For the love of Chriſt conſtraineth them.</hi> Now God, as he knows <hi>what number</hi> to imploy, ſo he gives <hi>divers gifts</hi> to divers men; but there is none <hi>can prove</hi> that he does not <hi>enable any</hi> with the Spirit of Propheſie but <hi>Schollers;</hi> For the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays <hi>plainly,</hi> writing to the Corinthians, <hi>What, came the word of God out from you,</hi> or <hi>came it onely unto you?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.38. Unto <hi>you</hi> only O Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies and Presbyters! ſurely not ſo: and he wiſhes them, wherefore <hi>Brethren covet to Propheſie;</hi> and yet theſe were not <hi>of the Presbyterie,</hi> but of the <hi>Believers,</hi> and if they might <hi>Propheſie,</hi> why not <hi>ours</hi> now? Why <hi>that</hi> debarred to <hi>believers</hi> now,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169784:12"/>more then it was in the Apoſtles times? Nay, <hi>why enjoyned</hi> as an excellent thing to Chriſtians, <hi>to learn to Preach</hi> then; and why <hi>prohibited,</hi> or thought <hi>unfitting</hi> to believers and <hi>gifted men</hi> in our days? They cannot ſay but that God doth <hi>now</hi> enable with <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>graces</hi> as he did then, <hi>his arm is not ſhortned,</hi> nor his love <hi>decayed;</hi> and our Presbyters cannot but <hi>acknowledge</hi> that <hi>they</hi> pray for God <hi>gracious</hi> aſſiſtance and for his <hi>gifts</hi> to be <hi>beſtowed</hi> upon them; and if ſo, <hi>others</hi> may have them aſ wel as <hi>themſelves,</hi> by Prayer; and then why not <hi>Preach</hi> as well as they? Or would they make the <hi>world</hi> believe that God hath <hi>tyed</hi> himſelf to beſtow thoſe <hi>peculiar</hi> gifts and graces to men of their <hi>Coat</hi> onely, and not to others, though in ſtrength of faith they ſhall <hi>petition</hi> the <hi>throne</hi> of Grace for them <hi>more</hi> than themſelves? and therefore there being ſuch puniſhments threatned <hi>to any,</hi> who do not imploy Gods <hi>gifts,</hi> whether <hi>Preaching,</hi> or any other; and ſuch <hi>rewards</hi> to them that ſhall put out <hi>their gifts;</hi> for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, that <hi>they</hi> (whoſoever they be) <hi>that turn many unto Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the ſtars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12.3. the reward is <hi>great,</hi> and indeed able to <hi>incite</hi> any that is able to <hi>follow</hi> that work, but the Prophet hath not <hi>tyed</hi> the reward onely to ſuch <hi>as conceive</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters <hi>ordained</hi> by men; But to <hi>any</hi> ſort of men whatſoever: though our Miniſters <hi>apply</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169784:12"/>that reward to themſelves <hi>alone,</hi> as though none ever <hi>converted</hi> any ſouls to <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> but they: and the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſays alſo of this reward; <hi>If any of your brethren do err from the truth, and one convert him, let him know that he hath ſaved a ſoul from death, and ſhall bide a Multitude of ſins,</hi> Jam. 5.19, 20. But the Apoſtle ſays here, if <hi>one (i.e.) any one</hi> of the brethren; for thus he writes, <hi>James</hi> 1.1. <hi>any one</hi> of all the twelve Tribes <hi>ſcattered</hi> abroad ſhall <hi>convert,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore any one that God hath given <hi>Ability</hi> of gifts and graces to; Let them <hi>ſet themſelves</hi> to work, and follow this <hi>ſpiritual</hi> plough; For their <hi>reward</hi> or <hi>puniſhment</hi> is upon <hi>following</hi> or <hi>failing, certain</hi> and <hi>ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, It was <hi>allowed</hi> of, and <hi>approved</hi> by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> nay ſays he, <hi>I do rejoyce therein, and will rejoyce, Phi.</hi> 1.18. at what good ſoul! That <hi>many of the brethren in the Lord waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to ſpeak the word without fear, Phil.</hi> 1.14. What's more plain? <hi>Many,</hi> and <hi>many</hi> of the brethren <hi>waxed bold to Preach,</hi> and at ver. 4,5. making <hi>requeſt with joy, for your fellowſhip in the Goſpel;</hi> in helping him in the <hi>Preaching</hi> of it; not onely the Biſhops and Deacons, but <hi>all the Saints</hi> alſo. Nay ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Some preach Chriſt of envy and ſtrife, and in contention, not ſincerely, what then? Nowithſtanding every way, whether in pretence, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169784:13"/>in truth, Chriſt is preached, and therein do I rejoyce,</hi> Phil. 1.16, 18. ſays he, <hi>and will rejoyce;</hi> here was a <hi>freedom</hi> for any of the <hi>believing brethren</hi> to <hi>ſpeak</hi> and <hi>Preach</hi> the word of God.</p>
            <p>And again, ſpeaking of the people of God. Phil. 2.15, 16. <hi>Ye ſhine</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>as lights in the world holding forth the word of life;</hi> was it <hi>good</hi> and <hi>commendable</hi> then, for any <hi>that could</hi> Preach, to do it, and is it to be thought <hi>unſeemly</hi> now? It is <hi>a happineſs</hi> to hear <hi>ſuch men,</hi> (let their <hi>profeſſion</hi> be never ſo mean) if they <hi>hold out</hi> the word of life; for Gods word <hi>is the ſavor of life unto life to them that believe.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. but mark <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> the words, and all men may <hi>ſee</hi> what <hi>good</hi> ſouls theſe were; though of <hi>ſeveral</hi> trades &amp; <hi>divers</hi> callings, they did not, <hi>would</hi> not hide the word, nor yet <hi>withold</hi> the word, but theſe held it out <hi>liberally, generally,</hi> to all, <hi>publickly, meekly, kindly, ſincerely,</hi> that all might <hi>ſee it,</hi> and <hi>underſtand</hi> it, that <hi>all</hi> might lay hold upon it, and have <hi>a ſhare</hi> in it, they held it our, ſo that the <hi>meaneſt</hi> capacity might <hi>apprehend</hi> it; and this a <hi>voluntary</hi> Act of theirs, and none <hi>blamed them</hi> for ſo doing; and as for the Apoſtle, he was <hi>glad at heart</hi> (good man) to ſee their <hi>boldneſs</hi> and excellent <hi>gifts</hi> in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet we may ſay, they were no Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters; nor <hi>ever were</hi> ordained by the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, nor <hi>ſet apart</hi> to the Miniſtry, and yet they <hi>held out</hi> the word for any to receive; What
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169784:13"/>can our <hi>Pulpit</hi> men, and ſuch as would have <hi>none</hi> to hold out <hi>the word</hi> but themſelves, ſay againſt this? they will not we hope (and vet they are bold enough) <hi>blame</hi> the Apoſtle, as ſuffering any thing that was <hi>diſorderly,</hi> or <hi>unfitting,</hi> neither can they <hi>juſtly</hi> blame the <hi>men,</hi> of what trade ſoever they were, for their Chriſtian <hi>Courage</hi> and ſincere <hi>Preaching;</hi> for they <hi>held out</hi> the word of life: a <hi>lawfull, juſtifiable</hi> and <hi>commendable</hi> Act; and therefore, <hi>what ſhould hinder,</hi> but that ſuch <hi>Tradſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> being <hi>ſo gifted</hi> and <hi>enabled</hi> with <hi>ſtrength</hi> of faith and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> knowledge, even in <hi>our</hi> days, may do <hi>the like;</hi> And laſtly, 'tis ſaid too, that the Apoſtle was <hi>ſo far</hi> from forbidding them, that he <hi>prayed</hi> in every <hi>Prayer,</hi> for their good ſucceſs; 'tis to be wiſhed that <hi>our</hi> Presbyterians <hi>were of the ſame mind</hi> too; but we <hi>haſt</hi> to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The <hi>Ark,</hi> the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> were all <hi>Types</hi> of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Temple</hi> of Chriſt; We know that there were <hi>men</hi> of <hi>ſundry Trades</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions;</hi> and indeed <hi>none other</hi> but <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> and <hi>Artificers</hi> did <hi>build</hi> any of thoſe <hi>three.</hi> For firſt, for the Ark, there were <hi>Carpenters, Sawyers, Smiths, Joyners,</hi> and many other Trades to make it up compleat and compact. So for the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> there were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>all</hi> Trades imployed to finiſh it; both theſe were made by Tradeſmen <hi>gifted</hi> and <hi>qualified</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169784:14"/>with wiſdom and skill; and no man; <hi>none of the Prieſts</hi> found fault with them for their labour. And ſo for the building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> there were <hi>hewers of wood</hi> 80000. in the mountains, and 60000. that bore <hi>burthens,</hi> and many thouſands that <hi>digged, cut</hi> and <hi>ſquared</hi> Stones; there were <hi>Braſiers,</hi> yes, and <hi>Gooldſmiths,</hi> and <hi>Silver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths,</hi> and <hi>Carvers,</hi> and <hi>Founders,</hi> with divers other <hi>Artificers</hi> yet <hi>by theſe</hi> that Temple was <hi>builded;</hi> nay, <hi>without theſe</hi> it had not been build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at all; yet in this <hi>great</hi> work, <hi>none</hi> was idle, <hi>all</hi> imployed, and their work was ſo <hi>exactly</hi> done, that it was <hi>renowned</hi> over the whole world; Now to ſay what's <hi>truth.</hi> In the <hi>building</hi> the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Temple, the <hi>Myſtical</hi> body of Chriſt, ſhall there be <hi>none allowed</hi> to work but the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Claſſical</hi> Elders? Alas, alas! If ſo, <hi>when</hi> will the <hi>work</hi> be done? It will go <hi>but ſlowly</hi> on if <hi>theſe onely</hi> are to be imployed.</p>
            <p>And further we do obſerve, that all the <hi>curious</hi> works of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed by <hi>gifted</hi> Tradeſmen, not a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Levite</hi> gave any <hi>Inſtructions;</hi> Nor had they <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> skill or Ability of <hi>knowledge</hi> in thoſe <hi>curious</hi> works, but God, (ſays the Text) put <hi>an excellent ſpirit of wiſdom into the hearts of the workmen, and ſo the work proſpered in their hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is wiſhed that no <hi>Tobiah's,</hi> and <hi>Sanbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats,</hi> would by falſe ſuggeſtions, or untrue Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169784:14"/>oppoſe theſe ſpiritual builders; If they ſhall, as God then raiſed up <hi>Cyrus,</hi> ſo will he now ſet up and advance pious <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to defend and incourage theſe ſpiritual Artificers: The work muſt be compleated, and 'tis high time to ſet to it; We hope none will grudge at it, for 'tis the Lords doing, and it is <hi>marvellous in our eyes;</hi> Shame and diſgrace will cover their faces, who do any ways retard it. Now why onely the Scribe, Doctor of the Law, and the wiſe men of this world imployed here? Nay, why not rather they debar'd? For Chriſts Temple is ſpiritual, and ſo they not able builders; and <hi>God,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, hath choſen the poor, and the weak, and the deſpiſed in the world to confound the great and the mighty;</hi> and we know the work is difficult, they that are put into this muſt have patience <hi>to bear great burthens,</hi> and heat, and cold, which many of our Presbyters are too nice to undergo; and they muſt work in the quarries of ſtone, upon men whoſe Conſciences are as hard as ſtone, they muſt temper Lime and morter, be in the dirt; behold here I pray, can we imagine that our neat and ſmooth Divines, ſo called, will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſuch <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Services</hi> accounted ſo <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did</hi> and <hi>mean?</hi> and yet by ſuch muſt the <hi>Spiritual Temple</hi> of Chriſt be <hi>accompliſhed</hi> and <hi>built;</hi> they muſt be ſuch as will be <hi>content</hi> to live <hi>hard,</hi> and lie <hi>hard,</hi> and have ſmall or no wages here perhaps,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169784:15"/>except <hi>ill reports,</hi> and to be accounted the <hi>of ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the world;</hi> and yet theſe hath God in his infinite wiſdom deſigned for the work; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will pray as <hi>Moſes, Proſper thou the work of our hands upon us, oh proſper thou our handy work.</hi> Pſal. 90. v ult. To conclude, the Church of Chriſt is by <hi>Solomon</hi> compared unto an Army: Now tis known that the Captains and Leaders of an Army were in the Jews wars, not onely of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> of <hi>Aarons</hi> loyns, but of all the other Tribes, and yet they <hi>inſtructed</hi> the Army, <hi>guided</hi> the Army, and made the Army <hi>compleat;</hi> and why not ſo now in our <hi>Spiritual war,</hi> ſhall there be none to <hi>Lead, Inſtruct, Guide</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage</hi> it but our Presbyters onely?</p>
            <p>And in the height of harveſt, any wiſe man wil be glad to ſee others willing to come to help him to reap and gather in his Corn into his Barn; and their work is the more commendable, becauſe 'tis freely offered and undergone, and prevents the danger of ſtormy weather; glad and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full husband men will be to ſee their Corn ſafe at home: ſurely 't would be an Act of ingratitude to rail at, or revile thoſe who help'd in the heat of the day: And is it not ſo in this ſpiritual harveſt? Our Presbyters ſhould rather rejoyce to ſee others ſo willing to help on the reaping and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Saints, eſpecially ſeeing now the harveſt of the earth is ripe, as 'tis <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. If
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169784:15"/>others to help forward the work, do put in their Sicles, and help to bring home, for fear of the raging ſtorm of perſecution, ſurely they deſerve thanks and commendation for their willing labours offered, and undertaken in this kind.</p>
            <p>To help forward a <hi>good work,</hi> in a time of need, is worth <hi>double</hi> thanks, and the more, when 'tis performed with <hi>willingneſs</hi> of minde; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if men ſhould prove <hi>ingratefull</hi> to ſuch for their voluntary labors, yet their reward is reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them by Chriſt himſelf. <hi>I know</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>whom I have truſted,</hi> and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. He ſays reſolutely: <hi>Henceforth there is a Crown of righteouſneſs laid up for me,</hi> &amp;c. And for all ſuch as do the Lords work willingly.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169784:16"/>
            <p>The Application is eaſie. Know O <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that God hath <hi>Curious, wiſe</hi> workmen, even <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> in theſe days, whom he <hi>daily</hi> does <hi>enable</hi> with gifts, to help on <hi>the gathering of the Saints,</hi> and to finiſh up the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Temple of Chriſt <hi>the Lord of life,</hi> to whoſe labors is <hi>wiſhed all</hi> good ſucceeſs and happineſs, and for whoſe <hi>encouragement</hi> this <hi>defence</hi> is ſet out, to the worlds <hi>veiw</hi> and <hi>cenſure;</hi> hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that none</hi> will be angry at it, for as much as it is <hi>intentively</hi> written, to <hi>uphold</hi> truth, and to <hi>propagate</hi> the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169784:16"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 51.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Do good in thy good pleaſure to Sion, build thou the walls of Jeruſalem.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mathew 9.37, 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then ſaith he to his Diſciples, the Harveſt truly is plenteous, but the Labourers are few.</p>
                  <p>Pray ye therefore the Lord of the Harveſt, that he would ſend forth Labourers into his Harveſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
